Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Your Majesty stayed up late with Lady Shen last night.
Why didn't Your Majesty sleep in a bit?
All the joy aside,
I had to hold court in the morning.
You didn't sleep well either, did you?
For one thing, I was overjoyed;
for another, I was instructing the Imperial Infirmary
to take good care of Lady Shen.
Your hard work is appreciated.
Noble Lady Shen...
Is there something Your Majesty needs?
I was thinking about promoting Noble Lady Shen.
Lady Shen has been favored by Your Majesty,
and now she is pregnant.
Her promotion can be reasonably expected.
But there's no precedent to promote a concubine
upon pregnancy or delivery.
It's not entirely because of her pregnancy.
Her steady personality is a rarity.
That is true.
Compared to Lady Sourire's keen intellect,
Lady Shen is responsible and decorous.
Does Your Majesty intend to promote
Lady Shen to Concubine?
- She's worthy of the title.
- Absolutely.
However, this would mean two Concubines
are the head of the Palace of Universal Happiness.
I'm afraid it would be inconvenient for Lady Shen
to move to another palace during her pregnancy.
Instead, why don't we double her happiness
when she gives birth to an heir?
You are right.
But I feel obliged to reward her.
Jewelry would be too paltry.
Since her promotion is temporarily delayed,
I wish to give her an honorary name in advance.
Your Majesty must have a name in mind already.
I'm thinking of naming her Vertu [惠Hui].
Virtuous and decorous - that perfectly describes her.
Lady Sourire and Lady Shen are like sisters.
Now they're truly on equal footing.
Your wish has come true. What a joyous occasion!
I don't see the joy of it.
All of a sudden I'm restricted from
doing everything and going anywhere.
It's such a bore!
There are nine more [lunar] months to come.
But the time will fly by.
Jinxi said that in the eighth month of your pregnancy,
your mother can come to the palace
and take care of you.
A family reunion of three generations.
Really? That's wonderful!
I’ve set my eyes on the baby in your belly.
When will you make me his honorary mother?
[a non-religious godmother]
What use are you as an honorary mother?
You'll be a mother soon as well.
We don't even know yet whether it's a boy or a girl.
I'll take anything!
I'm hoping for a prince I can rely on
for the rest of my life.
With the place you hold in His Majesty's heart,
he will love your child either way.
I'm afraid you'll be promoted
while you're still sitting the month [postpartum confinement].
Don't make fun of me.
I wanted to tell you something important.
I remembered it when I woke up this morning.
What could possibly be
more important than your pregnancy?
This is a serious matter.
Although Consort Fleur has lost power,
it's inevitable that she will rise again.
I'm afraid that you won't
be able to manage her on your own.
Looking with unclouded eyes, I don't expect His Majesty
to devote himself to just one woman.
Someone might take advantage of
the vacancy during my pregnancy.
Are you suggesting... that we bring Lingrong here?
Exactly.
Look at you!
You were the one who called her ruthless.
Now you wish she was here.
Well, being ruthless has its own benefits.
I don't want you to be on your own.
Let's get her here, so we won't be
at our wits' end if there is a crisis.
I will make the request to His Majesty
at his earliest convenience.
I don't believe he will refuse.
Now that you're His Majesty's number-one concubine,
all your requests will be granted.
But exerting yourself mentally can still harm your health.
The baby is your top priority.
You're right.
Sourire!
You've finally arrived.
- How was the trip?
- It was all right.
You shouldn't have been waiting for me outside.
It's such a hot day.
I hope you are not affected by the heat.
I was permitted to come here
all because Meizhuang put in a word for me.
How is she?
She's well.
She's even happier now that you're here.
On the way here, the eunuchs were saying that His Majesty
indulges all of Meizhuang's desires after she became pregnant.
"Seeing is believing." You'll see for yourself.
But before that, we shall pay respects to His Majesty.
I'll follow your advice.
Prince, you've been kneeling here for half a day now.
You should go back so as not to get sunstroke.
Mr. Su.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Peace to Companion An.
Mr. Su, who is that child?
That is the Fourth Prince.
He wishes to see His Majesty.
The Fourth Prince?
I've never heard of him.
He's been living here in the Summer Palace.
Does His Majesty not have time to see the Fourth Prince?
I'm afraid His Majesty is not in the mood to see you two either.
My Ladies, you should come at another time.
Sourire... Shall we ...
go back for now?
Poor child!
Sir, may I trouble you to send the Fourth Prince
some lotus seed soup to relieve the summer heat?
I will, My Lady.
Now that you're here, the gardens will be even livelier.
I would not be able to come
were it not for the care of you and Meizhuang.
Has Consort Fleur mended fences with His Majesty?
She lives far away from His Majesty's residence.
They don't get to see each other a lot.
Peace to My Ladies.
I bow in respect before Your Highness Lady Sourire.
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
Madam Zhang, this is Noble Lady Sourire.
My Lady.
Please rise, Fourth Prince.
We've never met before.
How did you know who I am?
Outside the Governance Hall, I could see Your Highness's
generous spirit even by a distant glimpse.
That was how I recognized Your Highness.
And Your Highness knew me as well.
Likewise, I had the same impression of you.
I share an affinity with Your Highness.
Thank you for remembering me.
This is Companion An.
Peace to Your Highness.
That is very courteous of you, Fourth Prince.
Lingrong, how about you go and have a look at your residence?
I will go with you to visit Meizhuang later.
I shall take my leave.
- Vermilion, you will go with her.
- Yes.
Madam Zhang, I wish to have a word with Lady Sourire.
Can you stand aside?
Madam Zhang seems to care a lot for you.
What would you like to say to me
that she can't even listen?
I hope Your Highness will forgive my intruding,
but I thought you could answer my question
because you know Imperial Father the best as his favorite concubine.
Your Highness, I simply wish to know ...
Is it true that Imperial Father doesn't like me?
Why would you think that way?
His Majesty is just too busy.
But why has he been keeping me here
for all these years and never visited me?
And he never lets me bow and pay respects to him
to fulfill my filial piety?
His Majesty is busy administering
all affairs under Heaven.
Although you've been living here and rarely seeing His Majesty,
he cares about you no less than the Fifth Prince.
The Fifth Prince has been living outside the Forbidden City as well.
The Fifth Prince has his mother, but I don't.
My mother was disdained for her low birth.
A man's value comes from within himself.
Although I know nothing about your mother,
I'm sure she loves you the same as every mother.
It doesn't matter what others think about you.
It's what you think of yourself that counts!
In the days to come, they will not dare to
have the least contempt for you.
For real?
You wouldn't have come to ask me if you didn't trust me.
I'm grateful for Your Highness's advice!
But why would you trust me the first time we met?
I think a concubine wouldn't win
Imperial Father's favor for no reason.
And I heard Your Highness is not even afraid of Consort Fleur.
I admire you as a person possessing bravery and brains.
I do not deserve your compliments.
I hope you will remember this:
instead of admire someone, become them.
Is Imperial Father really very busy?
If so, I will administer the country for him when I grow up.
Aiya,
you must not say such things.
Would you like to go have some snacks?
Sure!
Jiuzhou Qingyan
[The Peaceful Nine States]
This is such a nice place!
It's so pleasant and cooling in here.
The music comes from the lake
and can be best appreciated here.
The highly-ranked nobles are only allowed
to join the palace's most important celebrations.
I do not recognize any of the lords and ladies.
Do you know who they are?
That is Lord V, State Prince Heng [prince of the first rank],
with his Prince Consort.
The first one from the left looks very dignified.
He inspires awe in me.
But he seems very nice to his wife.
(State Prince Dun)
That is Lord X, whose mother was the younger sister
of the prior emperor's empress.
His lofty birth gives him an air of authority.
However, the prior emperor wasn't very fond of
Lord X for his notorious temper.
But Lord X is extremely nice to his wife.
They say a real man is defined by his might,
but in my eyes, a real man is defined by his love for his family.
Tenth brother, I'd like to make a toast
to you and your wife.
I thank Your Majesty.
Sourire, State Prince Dun seems
disrespectful to His Majesty.
Why is His Majesty so gracious to him?
After the nine princes' battle for the throne,
His Majesty must stabilize the government and the imperial family.
I wonder what's keeping my seventeenth brother this time.
He still hasn't appeared.
Your Majesty knows how he is.
He is bound by no rules.
[Venerable Prince Shen, the 21st prince of the prior emperor]
A family banquet isn't a big deal after all.
He's usually missing for such occasions. I'll let him be.
Lady Vertu, that is a very nice hairpin you're wearing.
Is it a new gift from the Empress Dowager?
Yes.
The Empress Dowager specially had the hairpin sent here
after hearing about Lady Vertu's pregnancy.
The Two Gods of Harmony on the hairpin will
bless her with plentiful children and good fortune.
The Empress Dowager received the hairpin when she was
pregnant with Lord XIV [enemy and brother of the emperor].
On that account, we can see how much the Empress Dowager
is looking forward to Lady Vertu's child.
I can't wait to see what an adorable prince he will be.
Who says it's a prince?
I'm hoping for a princess who's as adorable as Wenyi.
Enjoy.
(Consort Honnête)
Her Highness Consort Honnête.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesties.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty has again found beauty.
Consort Honnête, you haven't seen any new faces these years,
but you've kept the same eye.
You shouldn't have come on such a scorching hot day.
We're just celebrating a birthday.
It's nothing of significance.
Wenyi's first birth anniversary is a joyous occasion.
I must come to celebrate for her.
I haven't seen Wenyi for a long time.
- Take your seat.
- I thank Your Majesty.
It was at Wenyi's one-month banquet
when I last saw her.
Bring Wenyi to greet Her Highness quickly.
I would really like to hold her in my arms.
But I don't have the strength to.
I don't want to make her fall.
Auspice.
That choker was part of your dowry.
Why would you give such a valuable gift to a small child?
Your Majesty has a good memory.
Considering my persistent health condition,
it will be of no use if I keep it.
It is a perfect gift for the adorable Wenyi.
I thank Your Highness on behalf of Wenyi.
My pleasure.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组💃🏻
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
I wish to go out for a walk.
If His Majesty inquires, tell him I'll be back shortly.
Let's take a break here. My legs are sore from walking.
Mine as well.
Look, there are brocade carp.
Hold this for me.
- My Lady, why are you taking off your shoes?
- It's all right.
But what if someone sees you?
My Lady, you haven't changed at all.
Just as playful as you were back home.
Look, Vermilion, there are so many carp!
Great!
Let's go feel the water.
The water's rather cold.
Let's go down.
- I'm not going.
- There's nobody around.
My dress is new. I don't have the heart to soil it.
To soil it?
It's already soiled now!
My Lady, you have to make me two more dresses!
You'll wait for me up here then.
Hold on to me.
Be careful.
My Lady!
Who are you?
Get back!
Why do you care about me while you're almost a "drenched chicken"?
Who are you? How brazen of you!
Lord Li Yu described the hands of a lady as
"supple jade outstretched from emerald blue".
Today I learned that it is true.
But I think that is a more accurate description
for a lady's soft and fair feet.
Get me my shoes.
Here.
Your Lordship must mind your manners.
My Lady...
Vermilion, greet Noble Prince Guo.
[prince of the second rank]
We've never met before.
Why do you think I am Noble Prince Guo?
Whoever else in the palace would
always carry a flute on his person?
Whoever else could be drinking the tributary
Uygur Drunken Rose Liquor?
And whoever else dares to be so impertinent?
Do I reek heavily of alcohol?
My apologies.
Are you a new concubine of my brother?
This is Noble Lady Sourire.
I hope Your Lordship will forgive my offense.
His Lordship is inebriated. Please take care of him.
Yes.
We should go.
His Majesty is waiting for me.
I bid Your Lordship goodbye.
What is your name?
My humble name could taint Your Lordship's ears.
Your Lordship should have some rest to attain sobriety.
You must keep this to yourself.
If not, I'll have no burial ground for my corpse.
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
Please rise, rise quickly.
I noticed that you were feeling tipsy,
so I thought I should come check on you.
But when I came outside, you weren't around any more.
The wine was stronger than I expected
so I took a walk to sober up.
We observe one celebration after another.
The performance has begun to pall.
I want to give myself a break.
I wonder if you would like to join me in the side chamber.
I'm honored to obey Your Highness's gracious invitation.
Your Majesty, may I suggest that we dispense with
formality after the magnificent performance?
A family should not be sitting so stiffly for a meal.
How about we relax a bit on this joyous occasion?
What's your idea? Tell us.
Each and every concubine present has her special talents.
We can write down their talents and draw lots.
Whoever is selected will entertain our guests with her artistic flair.
What does Your Majesty think?
That is a fresh idea.
Let's draw lots.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Sourire, you have a good heart.
But in the palace, it is a bad thing
if all you have is a good heart.
You must remember that
your priority is always to protect yourself.
I'm grateful for Your Highness's advice.
I hope Your Highness can enlighten my dull-witted mind.
You've met the Fourth Prince.
He's bright and healthy.
But why does His Majesty avoid seeing him?
Have you thought from the perspective of His Majesty?
It was my negligence.
We've heard that a concubine can become
distinguished by an esteemed son
but it is also true the other way around.
His Majesty dislikes the Fourth Prince
because his mother was a menial maid at the Rehe Imperial Resort.
It happened when His Majesty was a noble prince.
One day His Majesty had a dispute with Lord VIII
and ended up drinking too much.
That was how he bestowed favor upon the maid
and that accidentally led to her having the Fourth Prince.
Lord VIII found out and reported this to the prior emperor
who censured our emperor for his misconduct
and nearly stripped him of his title.
The maid was unfortunately ugly
and from a humble background.
So His Majesty never liked her
and left her at the resort during her pregnancy.
Adding to her misfortune,
the maid died right after giving birth to her son.
So the Fourth Prince was all alone.
That is why the Fourth Prince
has always been kept in the Summer Palace?
"When the eyes don't see, the mind is at peace."
I am grateful for Your Highness's advice.
It's time that we should return.
Your Majesty, I have prepared the lots for drawing.
Since Lady Vertu is pregnant,
why don't I cast lots on her behalf?
You are the one who proposed the idea.
Now you don't want to participate?
I'm afraid I'm not talented in anything
other than making bead tassels.
It's nothing worth displaying in "the hall of grand elegance."
I've thought about it:
No matter what my sisters perform,
I will make a bead tassel to show my appreciation.
Does Your Majesty approve?
That's you being lazy, but I shall let it pass.
Aiya, how interesting.
We've all heard that every concubine in the palace is talented.
Seeing that for myself will open my eyes.
May we have the honor to have
Your Majesty to be our first presenter?
You are the mother of the birthday girl.
You can draw one for me.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty's exquisite calligraphy is requested,
to bestow on Wenyi your writing of the 夀 [longevity] character.
Before so many guests... This is putting pressure on me.
Your Majesty writes the finest calligraphy.
Lady Cao had great luck with her draw.
Your Majesty should not let her down.
All right, on Wenyi's first birthday,
I will write calligraphy as a gift for her.
I thank Your Majesty on Wenyi's behalf.
Your calligraphy has been advancing.
It's nothing worth mentioning.
I beg Your Majesties to excuse my offense.
I am feeling fatigued.
I cannot enjoy this joyous occasion here with you all.
You should go back and rest since you feel unwell.
I'll visit you when I get a chance.
I thank Your Majesty.
While Your Highness's health takes priority,
leaving the banquet so early might upset His Majesty.
If I stay I will only disappoint the troupe.
I've seen enough acts on their pretentious stage.
"When the eyes don't see, the mind is at peace."
This one is Lady Sourire's.
Please perform the Dance of the Startled Swan.
Your Majesty, Lady Sourire is as graceful as a swan.
The dance belongs to her.
The dance was created in the Tang Dynasty
by Emperor Xuanzong's Consort Mei.
It had been forgotten for many years.
But Empress Première adored dance,
and spared no effort to restore the choreography.
She painstakingly improved it
and her rendition stunned the nation.
That dance became a sensation in the palace.
It's very difficult to learn:
while a good performer can move like a swan,
a poor imitator will waddle like a duck.
Lady Sourire is very young.
How can she be experienced with this dance?
Lady Cao, you've assigned too demanding a task.
Nay, Lady Sourire has an exceptional aptitude.
Any girl can perform the Dance of the Startled Swan.
It is entirely understandable even if
she cannot dance as well as Empress Première.
We are sisters in a family.
No one will be strict with her performance.
I'm afraid I would only incur ridicule
for my unpresentable dancing skills.
You don't have to dance if you feel forced to.
I doubt that anyone today could compare with
the poise of Empress Première.
Your words are provocative, Consort Fleur.
If Lady Sourire declines, she will make
Lady Cao and Lady Vertu lose face at the ceremony.
That will also disappoint our guests.
If she agrees to dance but cannot deliver it well,
that will bring disgrace on herself.
And even if she dances well,
replicating the dance of Empress Première
might be considered disrespectful.
Your Majesty,
I've long heard of this Lady Sourire of yours.
They're saying that she is beautiful and talented,
but she can't even perform a dance.
I'm afraid she can't even compare
to the entertainers in my estate.
How can someone like this
deserve to serve Your Majesty?
Aiya,
"The lack of talent is a virtue for a woman."
Why does she have to perform
the Dance of the Startled Swan?
All she needs is to have a pretty face.
In that case, her reputation for beauty and talent is undeserved.
But earning favor with her beauty would only show
the shallowness of His Majesty's affection.
This dance is widely learned but rarely mastered.
How about we change to something else?
Your Majesty, Sourire has always immersed her heart in poetry
instead of singing and dancing.
I was wondering if she could compose
a poem for the princess?
It's been a long time since
this dance was performed in the palace.
I wish to see it as well.
Lady Sourire,
you can perform it however you like.
Please allow me to get changed in the side chamber.
I'll be back shortly, Your Majesty.
Using "the side chamber" [toilet] is certainly allowed,
as long as she's not escaping down the pit!
Don't talk drunkenly before His Majesty.
It is not that you don't know the dance, My Lady.
But now you're sitting astride a tiger
and there's no getting off.
What they want to see is not the grace of a startled swan
but simply a fleeing bird.
Help me get changed.
Your Majesty, I've changed to the costume.
Your Majesty, in addition to the ordinary instruments,
may I offer to play the zither
while Lingrong sings for Lady Sourire?
With great pleasure, Sourire.
Bring here Endless Longing, the zither.
When Consort Dowager Serein entered the palace,
the prior emperor gave her a gift as a symbol of love:
Endless Longing, the zither
and Eternal Promise, the flute.
After the prior emperor passed away,
Consort Dowager Serein requested to live in a nunnery.
So her zither and flute remain in the palace.
You share an affinity with this precious zither.
Swift as a startled swan;
Graceful as a spiraling dragon.
Glorious as the autumn chrysanthemums;
Vibrant as the spring pines.
Like the moon thinly veiled by the wisps of clouds;
Like the snow softly wafted by the flutters of a breeze.
From afar, she appeareth as the sun rising in the rosy sky;
Her moves are just a replication of Empress Première's.
Nigh, she is a lotus blooming above the emerald waters.
It's beautiful, but not at all original.
It's more important to be respectful than creative.
How many more surprises have you kept from me?
I hope my inferior dancing did not
incur ridicule from Your Majesty.
That was a marvelous performance indeed!
It could rival the best of my household performers.
Tenth Brother, you made an inappropriate comparison.
Lady Sourire performed the dance
in honor of Consort Mei's composition.
Emperor Xuanzong of Tang referred to
the dance as "the Spirit of Mei."
Today, I am fortunate to have admired
the long-lost grace of Consort Mei.
You have never witnessed
Consort Mei performing the dance.
How can you speak so certainly?
Tenth Brother, while I cannot compare to you
in archery or martial arts,
I did idle my years away reading more books of history.
We Manchus conquered the country with archery.
What is the use of the "stinking ink on history books"?
You're so full of the Han people's talk
because your mother is Han.
Our country needs masters of both pen and sword.
Brothers are like the fingers of one hand.
Everyone has his own strengths and weaknesses.
Don't compare length with breadth.
Like I said earlier, Your Majesty,
Lady Sourire is so talented to have mastered
an extraordinary dance.
I believe her dance is not beneath that of Empress Première.
If I recall correctly, not even Consort Fleur had entered
the family when Empress Première performed the dance.
Not to mention you, Lady Cao.
How could you possibly know how well Empress Première danced?
And how can you compare it to Lady Sourire's dance?
I hope Your Majesty will forgive my offense.
I have only heard of the stories.
It is my eternal regret to not
have seen the dance of the late empress.
Do you feel tired after all the dancing?
I'm all right, Your Majesty.
I did not have Heaven's blessings to admire
the splendid dance of the late empress.
My performance today was an imitation
of Consort Mei based on her music composition.
My dance to that of Empress Première
is what candlelight is to the moon.
Seventeenth Brother, you must punish yourself
with three cups of wine for your late arrival.
I have just played the flute to accompany
the dancing of your new concubine.
Imperial Brother, you must not punish me on her account.
Eternal Promise, the flute comes into
divine harmony with Endless Longing, the zither.
This is Noble Lady Sourire from the Zhen family.
This is Noble Lady Vertu from the Shen family.
And the singer is ...
I'm the Companion from the An family.
You're rewarded.
You, come sit next to me.
I thank Your Majesty.
Seventeen Brother, you've finally shown up.
Sit next to me!
Consort Fleur, what is the matter with you?
Why would you spoil the mood on such a joyous day?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.